Guide to the Joint Center for Political and Economic Studies records, 1966-2014 RL.11552
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Center Offices, 1969-2013
  - Office of Information Resources (OOR/Library), 1964-2013
    - OOR Subject files, 1972-2013
      - OOR Public policy, brochures and pamphlets, 1972-2013
        - Dual Eligibles and Part D, 2006 (Box 118)
        - Hyman, James B. - Men and Communities, 2006 (Box 118)
        - Jones, Ernestine F. - Public Policies and Practices in Child Welfare Systems that Affect Life Options for Children of Color, 2006 (Box 118)
        - Lindsey, Michael L. - The Impact of Waivers to Adult Court, Alternative Sentencing, and Alternatives to Incarceration on Young Men of Color, 2006 (Box 118)
        - Graddick, Tiffany - Never Again, 2006 Apr 11 (Box 118)
        - Morse, Reilly - Environmental Justice through the Eye of Hurricane Katrina, 2008 (Box 118)
        - Wenger, Michael R. - No More Katrinas, 2008 (Box 118)
        - Broadband Imperatives for African Americans, 2009 (Box 118)
        - Bositis, David A. - Opinion of African Americans on Climate Change and 2010 Midterm Elections, 2010 Feb (Box 118)
        - National Minority Broadband Adoption, 2010 Feb (Box 118)
        - Impact of Gender Based Violence on Stability and Security, 2011 (Box 118)
        - Climate Change, Environmental Challenges and Vulnerable Communities, 2012 Feb (Box 118)
        - Further to Go: Job Creation in African American Communities, 2013 Apr (Box 118)
      - OOR Politics and voting, files, 1964-2008
        Arranged chronologically and contains materials related to voting and politics such as published and unpublished essays, conference proceedings, studies, and research.
        - African Americans and the 1998 Midterm Elections, undated (Box 140)
        - Afro-Americans and the Living Constitution, undated (Box 143)
        - Black Conservative Americans, undated (Box 143)
        - Black Elected Officials in Southern States, undated (Box 143)
        - Black Leadership, undated (Box 143)
        - Blacks and Metro-Politics, undated (Box 140)
        - Cavanagh, Thomas E. - Black Voter Participation in the U.S., undated (Box 140)
        - Cavanagh, Thomas E. - Strategies for Voter Education Projects, undated (Box 140)
        - Community Outreach for Local Government Councillors Workbook, undated (Box 143)
        - Helping Blacks Participate Fully and Effectively in the Governance of Our Society, undated (Box 143)
        - It's About Time, video production, undated (Box 143)
        - The Long Road Up the Hill, African Americans in Congress: 1870-1983, undated (Box 143)
        - National Roster of Black Elected Officials, undated (Box 143)
        - Negro Officials - Johnson Administration, undated (Box 143)
        - Politics of Sex and Race in America, undated (Box 140)
        - Reactions to Ronald Reagan and Walter Mondale, polls, undated (Box 156)
        - Treatment of Minorities and Women in American History Textbooks in Secondary School, undated (Box 143)
        - The Black Vote, 1964-1976; 1966-1978 (Box 140)
        - Essays on Race and Politics, 1969; undated (Box 140)
        - National Black Roster of Elected Officials, 1969 Apr (Box 140)
        - The Black Man in American Politics, 1969 Dec (Box 142)
        - National Roster of Black Elected Officials, 1969 (Box 142)
        - Afro-Americans and the Living Constitution, 1970 (Box 142)
        - Levine-Reid Study of Black Representatives, 1970 Dec 15-1971 Apr 28 (Box 140)
        - Black political scientists, 1970-1971 (Box 142)
        - Survey to locate political scientists, 1971 (Box 156)
        - Federal Civil Rights Enforcement Effort, 1971 May 10 (Box 156)
        - Pettigrew, Thomas, proposal for survey research projects, 1971 Jul-1972 Sep (Box 142)
        - Dymally, Mervyn M. - The Black Politician, 1971 (Box 142)
        - New voters and elected officials, conferences, 1971-1972 (Box 142)
        - Congressional correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 142)
        - Congressional Black Caucus members, 1971-1973 (Box 142)
        - Black Caucus, 1971-1973 (Box 142)
        - Williams, Eddie N., speeches, 1971-1988 (Box 142)
        - Black Elected Officials in the South, 1972 Feb 3 (Box 142)
        - Baltimore's Failure to Elect a Black Mayor, 1972 Mar (Box 142)
        - The Black Electorate, Research Bulletin, 1972 Mar (Box 142)
        - Vernon, Gray C. - The Black Agenda, 1972 Apr 6 (Box 142)
        - HVD technical assistance follow up, service special project, 1973 Feb 22-Sep 25 (Box 142)
        - Bryce, Herrington J. - Black Women in Elective Offices, 1973 Aug (Box 140)
        - Southern Black Mayors, 1973 Nov (Box 140)
        - Fueling the Black Political Participation Movement, 1974 (Box 142)
        - Kilson, Margaret - Political Dilemma of Black Mayors, 1974 (Box 140)
        - Southern Black Mayors, 1974 Jun (Box 140)
        - Joint Center Analysis on Black Political Participation, 1975 (Box 140)
        - How to Encourage Black Political Participation in the Electoral Process, 1975 (Box 140)
        - Contributors to Third National Institute for Black Elected Officials, 1975 (Box 140)
        - Media coverage of the Third National Institute of Black Elected Officials, 1975 (Box 142)
        - Southern black mayors, interview transcripts, 1975 Jan 19 (Box 142)
        - The Federal A-95 Review Process, 1975 Apr (Box 142)
        - Meeting of the Caucus of Black Mayors, 1975 Dec (Box 142)
        - Third National Institute of Black Elected Public Officials, 1975 Dec 11-13 (Box 142)
        - Black Political Participation, 1975 Dec (Box 140)
        - Publications on politics, 1975; 1982-1984 (Box 142)
        - Operation Big Vote, 1976 (Box 140)
        - From Protest to Politics, 1977 Jan 14 (Box 142)
        - The Coordination Game, 1977 Jul (Box 142)
        - New Federalism and Community Development, 1977 (Box 142)
        - Institute on Local Government Planning, 1978 Feb 2-4 (Box 140)
        - North Carolina Second Annual Conference for Black Public Officials, 1978 Oct 12 (Box 142)
        - Roster of Black Federal Executives, 1978 Nov 2 (Box 140)
        - Election '78, 1979 Jan (Box 140)
        - The Black Vote, 1980 Jan (Box 140)
        - Newspapers, 1980 (Box 140)
        - Youth Leadership Development Program Workshop Curricula Guide, 1980 (Box 142)
        - Voting Rights Act, correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 142)
        - Williams, Eddie N. - The Black Vote in a Presidential Election Year, 1981 Feb (Box 140)
        - Local Government Management, 1981 Sep (Box 142)
        - Defner, Amanda - The Implications for the City of Mobile Case, 1981 Oct (Box 140)
        - Trends in the Characteristics of Black Elected Officials, 1982 (Box 140)
        - Desegregation of Black and Hispanic Students from 1968 to 1980, 1982 (Box 142)
        - On S. 1992 A Bill to Extend the Voting Rights Act, 1982 Feb 2 (Box 140)
        - Cavanagh, Thomas E. - The Characteristics of Black Elected Officials, 1982 Sep (Box 142)
        - The Impact of the Black Electorate, 1983 Feb (Box 140)
        - Black Employment in Municipal Governments, 1983 Feb 10 (Box 142)
        - Race in Politics, roundtable, 1983 Feb 16 (Box 142)
        - Race and Electoral Politics, 1983 Feb 16 (Box 142)
        - Outlook for a Black Presidential Candidacy, 1983 Mar (Box 140)
        - The Reagan Referendum, 1983 Apr 20-23 (Box 140)
        - Should a Black Run for President in 1984?, 1983 May 4 (Box 142)
        - Voter Law Policy Project, report, 1983 May (Box 140)
        - Cavanagh, Thomas E. - Black Voter Participation in the U.S., 1983 Sep (Box 140)
        - Lewis, David Levering - The Long Road up the Hill, 1984; 2 folders (Box 140)
        - National Coalition of Voter Participation, 1984 (Box 142)
        - The Runoff Primary, Blacks, and the Democratic Party, 1984 May (Box 140)
        - Endowment for Democracy, 1984 May 7 (Box 142)
        - Run-Off Primary Forum, 1984 May 10 (Box 142)
        - Runoff Primaries and Minority Political Participation, 1984 May 10 (Box 140)
        - Blacks and the 1984 Election, 1984 Nov 14; 2 folders (Box 142)
        - Crotty, William - The Presidential Nomination Process and Minority Candidates, 1985 Apr 30 (Box 140)
        - The Struggle for Voting Rights, 1985 Apr 3 (Box 143)
        - Black Women Elected Officials in the U.S., 1985 May (Box 140)
        - Black Voters Survey, 1985 Sep (Box 143)
        - Black Politics after the 1984 Election, 1985 Oct (Box 140)
        - Testimony, Frank R. Parker, 1985 Nov 20 (Box 143)
        - Black Elected Officials National Register, 1985 (Box 143)
        - Procedures for Administration of Section 5 of the Voting Rights Act of 1965, 1985 (Box 140)
        - Harris, Frederick C. - Post Reagan and the Emergence of a Bipartisan Black Electorate, 1986 Apr 2-5 (Box 140)
        - Parker, Frank R. - Mississippi's Massive Resistance to Black Political Empowerment, 1986 Apr 2-5 (Box 143)
        - Williams' published speeches, 1986 May 10-1991 Apr; undated (Box 143)
        - Gallup survey, 1986-1988 (Box 143)
        - Minority Business Set-aside Programs, 1986-1990 (Box 143)
        - Detroit Politics and Urban Theory, 1987 Apr (Box 140)
        - A Horse of a Different Color, press conference, 1987 Aug 19 (Box 143)
        - Congressional Black Caucus press conference, 1987 Aug (Box 143)
        - National Black Caucus of Local Elected Officials annual meeting, 1987 Dec (Box 143)
        - Census Information kit, 1987; 2 folders (Box 143)
        - Marion S. Barry Jr. v. United States of America, 1987 (Box 143)
        - Congressional Black Caucus, 1987-1988 (Box 143)
        - National Conference of Black Mayors 13th Annual meeting, 1987-1988 (Box 143)
        - Afropolis memorandum, 1987 Dec 21 (Box 143)
        - Picking a President, 1988 Feb (Box 140)
        - Symposium on Black Mayors, 1988 Feb 24 (Box 143)
        - Wells, Kimberly R. - Trends in Black Partisanship, 1989 May 3 (Box 140)
        - Public Opinion data correspondence, 1989 May 25 (Box 143)
        - Black Leadership Forum letter to President Bush, 1989 Jun (Box 143)
        - National Black Caucus of State Legislators, 1989 (Box 143)
        - Pre-1990 election analysis, 1989 (Box 143)
        - National Caucus and Center on Black Aged National Advisory Committee, 1989 (Box 143)
        - National Association of Black County Officials, 1989 (Box 143)
        - Black/Jewish Relations, 1989; 1993-1997 (Box 143)
        - Black Women in Politics, 1991 (Box 140)
        - Census meeting, 1990 (Box 143)
        - 1990 Census, Stand Up and Be Counted (Box 143)
        - National Symposium on Minority Aging, 1990 (Box 143)
        - Black judges, 1990-1992 (Box 143)
        - Meeting on Black-Jewish Relations, 1991 Jan 15 (Box 143)
        - Political Parties, Black Elites, and Recruitment, 1991 Apr 18-20 (Box 140)
        - Election data services, 1991 Apr 18 (Box 143)
        - Black American Attitudes Toward the Japanese, 1991 May (Box 143)
        - Brazil, 1991 (Box 143)
        - A Bill to Extend the Voting Rights Act, 1992 Sep (Box 140)
        - HBO Symposium, 1992 Jul (Box 140)
        - The Congressional Black Caucus in the 103rd Congress, 1993 (Box 140)
        - Black Elected Officials, 1993-1994; 2 folders (Box 140)
        - National Opinion Poll, 1996 April (Box 143)
        - African Americans Today, 1996 (Box 143)
        - African American Women and Political Empowerment, 1996 (Box 143)
        - Public Opinion, politics, 1998 Oct (Box 143)
        - Public Opinion, education, 1998 Oct (Box 143)
        - African American Clinton Appointees, 1999 (Box 143)
        - Black facts, NNPA, 2001 (Box 143)
        - Bositis, David A. - Channels in the River, 2002 Mar (Box 140)
        - Redistricting, 2002 May 22 (Box 140)
        - NAACP Public Forum on Civil Rights Enforcement, 2006 Jul 7 (Box 140)
        - Testimony of Roderick Harrison, 2008 Sep 23 (Box 140)
      - OOR Politics and voting, brochures and pamphlets, 1964-2012
        Includes publications produced by Joint Center contains printed materials, including pamphlets and brochures, that address African American voting trends and election campaigns for use by government representatives and the general public. The materials did not have a discernible original order and have been arranged chronologically.
        - Black voting trends, 1964-2012; 6 folders (Box 120)
        - Black Caucus and black politics, 1971-1975; 1972-1976; 1980-1984; 3 folders (Box 122)
        - Voter mobilization, 1971-1984; 1987-1999; undated; 2 folders (Box 122)
        - Democratic and Republican National Conventions, 1972; 1976-2012; 7 folders (Box 122)
        - Redistricting and devolution, 1973-1996; 2 folders (Box 122)
        - Black politics, 1974-1985; 1991-2009; undated; 5 folders (Box 122)
        - Voting Rights Act, 1975-2012; 6 folders (Box 120)
        - Black elected officials, guides and research, 1977-2001; 6 folders (Box 120)
        - Voter campaigns, 1980-1983 (Box 122)
        - Election reports, 1984 (Box 120)
        - Voting publications, 1984-1994 (Box 133)
        - National opinion polls, 1996-2008; 2 folders (Box 120)
      - OOR South Africa office, files, 1990-2002
        In 1993 the Joint Center's Office of International Affairs opened an office in Johannesburg, South Africa, to provide political assistance activities and legislative training to new post-Apartheid political parties. Research studies and projects focused on voter education and governance, youth HIV/AIDS programs in partnership with Schools Health and Population Education (SHAPE), and women's empowerment. Prior to the opening of the office, the Joint Center conducted economic, governance, and voting forums and summits. Materials are arranged chronologically.
        - Ballot Paper, South Africa, undated (Box 185)
        - Building Democratic Models of Communications mayor's workshop, undated (Box 145)
        - Final report on Opinion Poll in Qwaqwa/Free State, undated (Box 145)
        - National Summit on Africa, undated (Box 145)
        - Opinion Poll in the Northern Province report, undated (Box 145)
        - Report on the poll in Thohoyandou/Northern Province, undated (Box 145)
        - South Africa slides and photos, undated (Box 145)
        - Summary of Investigation of Training Needs of Women Councilors, undated (Box 145)
        - Oscar Dhlomo forum, 1990 (Box 145)
        - Dhlomo, Oscar, 1990 Sep 2 (Box 145)
        - Dhlomo speech, 1990-1991 (Box 145)
        - Annual reports, 1993; 2000 (Box 145)
        - Pamphlet on the South African Transition to Democratic Rule, 1994 Apr (Box 145)
        - Voter Education, Violence and the South African Elections luncheon forum, 1994 Apr (Box 145)
        - Statement of Capabilities: Experience with Africans NGOs, 1994 Jul (Box 145)
        - A Youth Policy for South Africa, 1995 (Box 145)
        - South Africa Project pamphlets and brochures, 1995; 2001; 2003 (Box 145)
        - Research Project on the Presidential Elections in Benin, 1996 (Box 145)
        - Explanatory memorandum on the Constitutional Assembly, 1996 May 8 (Box 145)
        - West Rand Report by Ntlokoa, Laurence, 1996 Aug (Box 145)
        - East Rand and Khayalami constituency report by Sibiya, Vusi C.T., 1996 Oct (Box 145)
        - Northern Gauteng Province and Eastern Region-North West Province Report by Ntuli, Benjamin S., 1996 Oct (Box 145)
        - Northern Province research database document, 1997 (Box 145)
        - Promoting Excellence in Community Research workbook, 1998 May 7-9 (Box 145)
        - Gender Empowerment and Access Program proposal, 2000 (Box 145)
        - Grants correspondence, 2000 (Box 145)
        - National Council of Negro Women decision memos, 2000 (Box 145)
        - National Council of Negro Women Nigeria budget, 2000 (Box 145)
        - Newsletters on South Africa Project, 2000-2001 (Box 145)
        - Access, Public Policy Reform, Information, Service and Employment program for people with disabilities, 2000 Sep 15 (Box 145)
        - International Foundation for Education and Self-help, 2000 Nov 1 (Box 145)
        - Lesotho concept paper, 2001 Jul (Box 145)
        - Department for International Development in Southern Africa, 2002 (Box 145)
        - HIV/AIDS, Economics, and Governance in South Africa, 2002 (Box 145)
        - Memorandum of understanding between Joint Center and NPLGA, 2002 (Box 145)
      - OOR Southern Regional Council, brochures and pamphlets, 1946-1984
        This subseries is arranged chronologically and contains original publications from the Southern Regional Council, an organization founded in 1944 to avoid racial violence and promote racial equality in the Southern United States. The Joint Center used the Southern Regional Council's voter registration and political-awareness publications and programs as references for its related work.
        - Henderson, Vivian W. - The Economic Status of Negros, undated (Box 155)
        - Race in the news: Usage in Southern Newspapers, undated (Box 155)
        - Price, Margaret - The Condition of Our Rights, undated (Box 155)
        - Policy Research, Information, Government Monitoring, Leadership Development ...for a New Age in Accountability, undated (Box 155)
        - Muse, Benjamin - Memphis, undated (Box 155)
        - Hungry Children, undated (Box 155)
        - Vance, Rupert B. - Wanted: The South and Future for the Nation, 1946 (Box 155)
        - Questions and Answers: The Schools and the Courts, 1953 Aug (Box 155)
        - Answers for Action: Schools in the South, 1954 Jun-Jul (Box 155)
        - Changing Patterns in the New South, 1954 Dec-1955 Jan (Box 155)
        - Intimidation Reprisal and Violence in the South's Racial Crisis, 1955-59 (Box 155)
        - Background Summary on Charlottesville, Arlington, Norfolk, and Newport News, 1958 Aug 11 (Box 155)
        - Background Summary on Virginia, 1958 Aug 11 (Box 155)
        - State vs. Federal Authority in Virginia: A Background Memo, 1958 Aug 22 (Box 155)
        - Little Rock: A Look at the Record, 1958 Sep 16 (Box 155)
        - The Southern Regional Council - Its Origin and Aims, 1959-1963 (Box 155)
        - Waiting Room Practices in 21 Southern Cities, 1959 Jul 17 (Box 155)
        - New Releases, 1961; 1963 (Box 155)
        - The Freedom Ride, 1961 May 30 (Box 155)
        - Zinn, Howard - Albany, 1962 Jan 8 (Box 155)
        - A Study for Negro Farmers in South Carolina, 1962 Dec (Box 155)
        - The Civil Rights Crisis: A Synopsis of Recent Developments, 1963 Jun 25 (Box 155)
        - Charlotte Has Built It's Integration Road, 1963 Aug 1 (Box 155)
        - Civil Rights: A Year-End Summary, 1963 Dec 3 (Box 155)
        - New South: The Southern Regional Council 1944-1964, 1964 Jan (Box 155)
        - Watters, Pat - Charlotte, 1964 May (Box 155)
        - Muse, Benjamin - Louisville, 1964 May (Box 155)
        - The Price We Pay for Discrimination, 1964 Jun (Box 155)
        - Law Enforcement in Mississippi, 1964 Jun 14 (Box 155)
        - Post Civil Rights Act Passage, 1964 Jul 28 (Box 155)
        - Watter, Pat - Brunswick, 1964 Sep (Box 155)
        - Watters, Pat - Encounter with the Future, 1965 May (Box 155)
        - Coles, Robert, M.D. - The Migrant Farmer, 1965 Sep (Box 155)
        - Southern Justice: An Indictment, 1965 Oct 18 (Box 155)
        - Dell Gimarc, Jerry - A Home of Our Own, 1966 (Box 155)
        - Annual Report of the Executive Director of the Southern Regional Council, 1966 Jan (Box 155)
        - Neighborhood Stabilization, 1966 May (Box 155)
        - Public Assistance in the South, 1966 Nov (Box 155)
        - School Desegregation 1966: The Slow Undoing, 1966 Dec (Box 155)
        - Price, Margaret - The Condition of Our Rights, 1967 (Box 155)
        - Chesler, Mark A. - In Their Own Words: A Student Appraisal of What Happened After School Desegregation, 1967 Jan (Box 155)
        - Slum Ghettos in Your Town, 1967 Feb (Box 155)
        - Collins, Patricia - How to Conduct a Registration Campaign, 1967 May (Box 155)
        - On the National Crisis, 1967 Aug (Box 155)
        - Clark, Kenneth B. - The Present Dilemma of the Negro, 1967 Nov 2 (Box 155)
        - Voter Registration in the South, 1968 (Box 155)
        - Black Youth in a Southern Metropolis, 1968 Jan (Box 155)
        - A Review of Program Activities During 1967, 1968 Jan (Box 155)
        - Watters, Pat and Weldon Rougeau - Events at Orangeburg, 1968 Feb 25 (Box 155)
        - Weltner, Charles Longstreet - John Willie Reed: An Epitaph, 1969 (Box 155)
        - Ulmer, Al - Cooperatives and Poor People in the South, 1969 Mar (Box 155)
        - Race Makes the Difference, 1969 Mar (Box 155)
        - Watters, Pat with J. Edwin Stanfield - In Memphis: One Year Later, 1969 Apr 4 (Box 155)
        - Dunbar, Anthony - The Will to Survive, 1969 Jun (Box 155)
        - Walls, Dwayne - Fayette County, Tennessee: Tragedy and Confrontation, 1969 Oct (Box 155)
        - The Federal Retreat in School Desegregation, 1969 Dec (Box 155)
        - Walls, Dwayne - The Chickenbone Special, 1970 Mar (Box 155)
        - A Review of Program Activities During 1971, 1972 Feb (Box 155)
        - An Analysis of Voting Patterns in Alabama and Georgia, 1984 (Box 155)
      - OOR Committee on Policy for Racial Justice, files, 1981-1990
        In 1981 and 1982, the Joint Center, Kenneth B. Clark, and John Hope Franklin assembled twenty-five scholars and policy leaders to discuss their publication, The Nineteen Eighties: Prologue and Prospect. The Committee for Policy on Racial Justice proceedings held in Tarrytown, New York yielded wide-ranging discussions about the effects of racism on African American families especially concerning the economy and education. The materials containing transcripts, correspondence, and reports, are arranged chronologically.
        - Committee on Policy for Racial Justice - meeting at Tarrytown, proceedings, 1981-1982; 1993-1994; 23 folders (Box 136)
        - Tarrytown summary, 1982 Aug 20 (Box 136)
        - Policy conference, 1982 Nov 19-21 (Box 136)
        - A Policy Framework for Racial Justice, 1985 Apr 4-6; 2 folders (Box 136)
        - Committee on Policy for Racial Justice - background readings, 1986 Apr 25 (Box 136)
        - Committee on Policy for Racial Justice - correspondence, 1988-1992 (Box 136)
        - Committee on Policy for Racial Justice - meeting at Fairfax, transcript, 1990 Sep 28 (Box 136)
      - OOR TV violence, files, 1993-1995
        Arranged chronologically and contains meeting minutes, project descriptions, and reports related to a project addressing the effects of television violence on adolescents. The project was funded by the Pew Research Center.
        - Advisory council members, 1994 (Box 130)
        - Advisory council meetings, 1994 (Box 130)
        - Contacts, 1993-1994 (Box 130)
        - Final report to the Pew Charitable Trust, correspondence, 1994 Oct (Box 130)
        - Final report to the Pew Charitable Trust, recommendations section draft, 1994 (Box 130)
        - Final report to the Pew Charitable Trust, draft, 1994 (Box 130)
        - First advisory council meeting on children and TV violence, 1994; 2 folders (Box 130)
        - Grant implementation meeting, 1994 (Box 130)
        - Hewes, Larry, meetings, 1994 Jul (Box 130)
        - Joint Center involvement with Pew project, 1994-1995 (Box 130)
        - Laurence, Hewes I., III, resume, 1993 (Box 130)
        - Leadership, 1994 (Box 130)
        - Missing laptop, 1994 (Box 130)
        - Other correspondence, 1994 (Box 130)
        - Procurement Requests, 1994 (Box 130)
        - Recommendations memo, 1994 Jan; Apr (Box 130)
        - Second advisory council meeting, 1994 Sep (Box 130)